Hello and welcome to 170A.
I am here to show you how to set up
GitHub so that you can host some
stuff on a repository.
My name is Abram Stern.
I'm your instructor this quarter.
And I co designed this
class with Warren Sack.
So you'll hear my voice in the code talk
throughs little bit later in the
quarter, not so much later.
And Warren, Professor Warren Sack on the
lectures, we collaborated on this and
class benefited from having two cooks.
So this window here is my GitHub account.
And this video, this brief video
walkthrough assumes that
you have already registered [for Github].
There are some other services you can use
since the wrong window.
Okay, we're over here.
GitLab.com is another one that you could
use if you really don't
want to use GitHub.
And then there's Codeberg.org.
Codeberg is based in the EU.
They have various privacy settings and
they don't allow the use of AI in
any of their projects.
So all of these sites have their
own pages capability feature.
But they're all a little bit different
and GitHub is the easiest to set up.
So if you're just getting started and you
don't have any major problem using
GitHub, I recommend doing that.
And if you want to use one of these other
ones, maybe you're a
little more advanced.
That's fine too.
And if you get stuck trying to get things
working, feel free to reach out.
But otherwise, I'm going to be showing
how to use GitHub for this.
So your page may look
a little bit different.
For instance, you may
not have 67 repositories.
What have I been doing with my life?
And your background might be white.
I am dark mode all the time.
So that's why my page looks like this.
I'm going to make a new repository.
And I do that here from this plus sign up
here, this plus menu
that makes new things.
And I'm going to make a repository to
store all of the assets
for my 170A project.
And if you want to be really organized,
you could make a repository for each of
your projects, even though you're going
to be basically hosting them on CodePen
if you also wanted to have them on here.
So you had a version that just ran full
screen without CodePen's
triple window stuff.
You can do that.
And it's not so hard.
If you want to put everything in one
repository, that's OK, too.
You can upload images, sounds, HTML
files, JavaScript, CSS, you name it.
The main thing to avoid is trying to
upload files that are
more than 100 megabytes.
And when we get into video later in the
quarter, that may be a
wall you run into.
And we can work on that then.
So I'm just going to call
this FDM170A_Projects.
And it will be underneath the owner name.
So this is your account name here.
And then this is this.
So each person can have a repository name
that is like, the repository
names can be identical.
Since the address is beneath the
username, they don't collide.
And this will be some files to support my
projects, images and such,
and a smiley face.
Because I grew up before emoji, so I
still type them by hand.
Visibility public is important.
If you don't want your projects to be
publicly available, that makes things
quite a bit more complicated.
We can work around that.
It's really a hard line for you.
But public should be default here.
And this other stuff is just
fine as it is.
We're going to create repository and it's
going to say like, hey, this is empty.
Don't you want to do something?
And for instance, setting up GitHub
Copilot, which is Microsoft's like AI
companion, which I would
prefer you didn't use.
You can add collaborators so that you can
share code and like deal with the
versioning of a project as
it changes over time.
Git is the underlying technology that all
three of these sites use.
And then GitHub, GitLab, and Codeberg
each implement their own kind of
architecture around Git that adds social
features like issues, like reporting
bugs, pull requests, like somebody else
making a change and submitting
it for review.
Like that's social architecture on top of
the versioning architecture of Git.
And you're going to see these like
command line things that you could type
if you installed Git
and used your terminal.
We're not going to worry
about that right now.
We're just going to use the web page.
So it's saying we can get started by
creating a new file and they have a web
based text editor that you can do to
just edit files in your browser and save
them in your repository.
Oh, there's a dash in my, did
I really do that?
I didn't mean to do that.
Well, you can call yours
whatever you want.
I unintentionally put
a hyphen after project.
I don't know how I did that.
Anyway, I'm going to upload an existing
file and it gives you this dialogue
that's familiar from
other websites I imagine.
And I'm going to drag this file of
"rosie_a.png"
Rosie is a dog that my partner and I take
care of and take for walks every day.
She's a sweet girl.
And now it's asking me to commit changes.
And so part of Git is that
there are commit messages.
Every time you make a change to the
repository, you're making a note
about what you did.
And this is like a trail of bread crumbs
that you can follow backwards in time
over the growth of a project.
If you make a ton of changes and commit
them all together, you don't have the
granularity of change this file, change
this file change this file.
In this case, I just uploaded Rosie.
So all of this is so that we can host
images and media and use them in CodePen
because they will host the HTML, the
CSS, all the text stuff.
Text, not tech, but it's also
kind of tech, right?
But they don't really have a file
upload thing for images.
So previously, UCSC had their own web
server that everybody got an account on,
students, staff, and faculty.
And it had its quirks, but it was nice.
But that hasn't existed for
a few years now.
Then we were using Dropbox in a way that
Dropbox really wasn't
meant for: hotlinking images.
And you ended up with these URLs that are
like 17 miles long with lots of random
looking numbers in it.
I'm sorry, that's, I'll stop that.
GitHub Pages is the lowest hanging fruit
to solve this problem.
It gives us a way to host files on the
web as though on a webpage that we can
then link from outside.
So if I want to use this image of Rosie
in a project, I can host it on pages and
I can host my whole project on here too.
So how do we do that?
Well, there's a menu up here
in our project, right?
Code issues, pull requests.
These are all for this repository.
And because I've bumped the font size up
to make this video easier to read,
settings was getting hidden
in the more menu.
See?
More over here, settings.
But if it's wide then
we get settings here.
So settings is where we want.
And this is a lot of stuff that we don't
need to worry about.
Some of it's pretty complicated.
Actions and webhooks are like code that
we can write that will automatically
happen every time the code changes, to
sort of like test things.
And like we're not doing that.
Pages is what we want.
So we go to pages.
And GitHub Pages is designed to host
personal organization or project pages
on the GitHub repository.
So there's only one thing we really
need to do here.
Git repositories have different branches.
There will be like a main branch.
There could also be an
experimental branch.
If you're like kind of going back and
forth between like something you're
working on and something that's public.
At this stage, if you're your process as
an emerging digital media producer, as a
emerging creative coder, you don't
really need to worry about that yet.
It's kind of more advanced stuff,
especially as you start working on
projects with multiple people someday.
And so we only have one
branch in our project.
It's called main.
But even though there's only one branch,
that's not what's selected by
default in GitHub Pages.
So we have to hit main.
We leave this at root.
If we wanted to set a different directory
in our repository to host the pages
from, we could do that.
But we don't need to.
And I hit save.
So it's building the web page out of the
files that I've uploaded.
Right now, it's just an image.
So sometimes that takes a
little bit of time.
This is a free service.
It hasn't finished yet.
It's currently being built
from the main branch.
See that?
I'm going to hit reload again.
The URL will be a predictable
one, which is nice.
So just any minute now.
Sometimes you get what you
pay for it, right?
Sometimes it'll take a whole minute,
which in between saving something and
wanting to test it can feel
like a long time.
So here we go.
And it's saying page not found.
But if I go to rosie_a.png,
here's Rosie.
That's great.
Hi, Rosie.
Why did it say page not found?
So web servers generally will look for a
file underneath that last slash, right?
And this URL up here, it's HTTPS.
That's a secure hypertext
transfer protocol.
And this is my username
on GitHub. - github.io.
It's not dot com.
It's dot io.
And then it's slash.
And it's the repository name with the
dash in it, which I didn't really want.
But there it is.
If we just wanted to have something load
at this address without designating a
file name, then we need
a file called index.html.
So if I go to code here, we
have our one file.
Well, we want another file.
We're going to create a new file.
I'm going to call this index.html.
And I'm just going to make a really bare
bones piece of HTML.
We'll have HTML.
We will have a head.
You can see it has some
syntax highlighting.
That's nice.
Title.
We'll have a body.
And I'm using the image tag, which if you
haven't already learned
about, you're about to.
This will put an image on the page.
And it's loading from the
same directory we're in.
So I don't need to do any pathing.
And I don't any HTTP.
So I am going to commit my changes.
I'm going to say, yeah,
create index.html.
That's great.
That's descriptive.
That's actually what I'm doing.
And automatically, in about a minute, our
page not found is going to change.
So when you're working in CodePen, you're
going to be on a different site
than the GitHub asset.
And so what is the URL going to be for
the image that's over here?
Well, we'll look at that in a second.
So we can see that there's a URL here.
If I open this in a new tab, we're going
to get this embedded in a viewer here.
There's an alpha channel on this PNG,
which is why the black background is
showing through, as opposed
to the white box.
And if we open the image in a new tab,
then we get this long URL here of
raw.github user content with my username
and the repository name, and then
refs, heads, main, rosie.
That's a lot.
Even if you're copying and pasting, copy
and paste this into code
pen, it probably works.
But better than that, if I reload this,
see, now our HTML is loading.
The index.html does not appear in the
URL, but it is implicitly being loaded.
So in the same way, rosy.underscorea.png,
it's like the URL is predictable.
It's aphid.github.io, or your
username.githube.io, slash the
repository name, slash whatever
the file name is.
And if you remember that pattern, yes,
you can copy and paste from here, but
you can also kind of freehand it,
because you know how it's going to be.
https colon, my username.github.io, slash
ftm, whatever you called your
repository, slash whatever
the file name is.
And you can embed sounds, you can embed
other CSS files and things, and you'll
be learning how to do all of that.
But I just wanted to get you to the point
where you can upload some images and
access them on another page.
So yeah.
Hopefully that was clear, but I will be
hanging out in the chat
room for the class.
I will be looking at my email.
And if you need help, please ask, because
this is something that we'll
be using all quarter.
And so let's get it right in week ones,
so that the rest of the quarter, you can
focus on the code.
Well, thanks for sticking around
for all of that.
And I look forward to working with you
and seeing what you make.
So have a good one and take care.